Guide to the Eadweard Muybridge Photograph Collection 1878, circa 1887 PR 205
New-York Historical Society
Eadweard Muybridge photograph collection
1878, circa 1887
New-York Historical Society
Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904
PR 205
2 Linear feet in 1 box containing 10 folders
Collection includes a 13 plate photographic panorama of San Francisco, 1878, and 23 collotype plates from Muybridge's published series of photographs "Animal Locomotion" (Philadelphia Photogravure Company of New York, 1887).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Biographical / Historical
Eadweard Muybridge (1830-1904) was an English photographer who worked extensively in the United States from 1852 on. He was a pioneer in studies of human and animal locomotion that led to the development of motion picture film.
Existence and Location of Copies
The San Francisco panorama images have been digitized and can be found in N-YHS's digital library
Scope and Contents
Collection includes a 13 plate photographic panorama of San Francisco, 1878, and 23 collotype plates from Muybridge's published series of photographs "Animal Locomotion" (Philadelphia Photogravure Company of New York, 1887). The locomotion collotype plate numbers are: 44, 62, 66, 152, 273, 278, 319, 327, 348, 355, 374, 386, 461, 478, 512, 573, 590, 640, 658, 673, 721, 735, and 758.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The panorama was purchased by Daniel Parish on behalf of the New-York Historical Society in 1897. The "Animal Locomotion" plates were a gift from James Strobridge in 1952.
Albumen prints.; Cityscapes (representations); Collotypes (prints); Panoramas (visual works); Animal locomotion -- Photographs.; California Street (San Francisco, Calif.) -- Photographs.; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Photographs.
- Series I. Panorama from California Street Hill, 1878
  Scope and Contents
  13 albumen prints creating a panorama.
  These images of San Franscisco have been digitized and can be found in N-YHS's digital library
  - Plates 1-3, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plates 4-6, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Plates 7-9, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Plates 10-13, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Animal Locomotion, circa 1887
  23 collotype prints from Muybridge's published series, "Animal Locomotion" (Philadelphia Photogravure Company of New York, 1887). A copy of this can be found in N-YHS's catalog.
  - Plates 44, 62, 66, 152, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Plates 273, 278, 319, 327, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Plates 348, 355, 374, 386, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Plates 461, 478, 512, 573, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Plates 590, 640, 658, 673, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Plates 721, 735, 758, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 10)